Stanford
University uh the last time as I
remember and I have a poor memory so
correct me if I'm wrong we talked about
magnets
and did we talk about phase Transitions
and mean field approximation and I
showed you how the phase transition
between a magnetized uh well how the
phase transition happens to a magnetic
system the simple magnetic system the
magnetic system being the
system on a lattice where every spin is
coupled to its nearest neighbor by a
term in the energy which seeks to align
them in other words the energy is lowest
when the spins neighboring spins are
aligned uh the ground state of that the
lowest energy
State and which describes zero
temperature is all spins perfectly
aligned as you begin to heat it up a
little bit the spins begin to jiggle a
little bit um but any spin still has a
bunch of neighbors around
it and particularly if the dimension of
the system is very high and actually for
our purposes three dimensions is pretty
high
uh then the number of bonds connecting
that spin to its neighbor Neighbors are
also high and so I showed you how to use
the mean field
approximation to calculate mean field
approximation simply means uh postulate
an average for all the spins and in
particular in this case it means all the
spins neighboring to our Target spin to
the spin that we are uh going to focus
on
and just imagine that they are frozen at
their average value these spins are
frozen at their average value that gives
you an expression for the energy of the
one spin that is left over the one at
the
center and in a sense the other spins
surrounding it give it a uh bias to
point in the same direction as the
average spin of the
others the higher the dimensionality
the more neighboring spins there are the
better are the approximation of saying
you can average over
them but that's the basic idea of the
mean field approximation and then let me
let me remind you what you do you
calculate in the background of the other
spins you calculate the partition
function for the one extra spin you then
calculate the average magnetization of
the extra spin in other words you
calculate
the average value
of Sigma of the extra spin
there what was it equal to anybody
remember the formula for
it I don't remember the formula for
it I just want to go back and uh minus
the average energy over
2 2 SD no no but there was a a formula
with a tangent a hyperbolic tangent
yeah hyperbolic tangent to Beta
s hyperbolic
tangent of 2 Beta SD 2 Beta
SD D is the dimensionality of space and
it simply represents the number of
nearest neighbors to this fellow over
here all right beta is the inverse
temperature where did the two come from
oh I remember where the two came from hm
two * yeah because ER because the number
of nearest neighbors is twice the
dimensionality and S was the average
spin at the uh the average spin of the
entire ensemble of
spins and then the consistency requires
that this be the same as s in other
words this spin is no different than all
the others I said that all the others
have an average spin s and we get a
consistency equation s is equal to
tan 2 Beta s *
D and if we can solve that equation then
we will determine what the average
magnetization is as a function of the
other variables in the problem beta D
and so forth all right so let me just
remind you what that looked
like we plot
s s is just a linear function s of what
s of
s right we plot s of s s of s is just a
straight line S equals
s uh and then we superimpose on that the
graph of tan twice beta
SD and that looks something like
this let's see if the temperature is
high when the temperature is high that
means that beta is
small then the tan function looks like
this it's very flat it asmp tootes to
one it's linear at the origin here
but the slope is less than the slope of
this great line over here and so there's
no intersection there's no intersection
of this blue curve with a black curve
other than the origin and that means the
only
solution to this problem is that s
equals
0o now we
start decreasing the temperature that
means increasing beta and we discover
that this curve moves
in and eventually its slope at the
origin will become equal to one
when you go beyond that the Curve will
look like
this and you have two new
Solutions these two solutions are in
fact the stable Solutions it's possible
to prove that this solution over here
really is unstable that if you try to
make uh if you try to um make the magnet
behave as this solution tells you any
tiny little per ation will in other
words uh over here what does it say it
says that the magnetization is zero how
do you make the magnetization equals
zero if it doesn't want to be zero if it
wants to all line up well you simply
take the two possibilities all lined up
one
way plus all lined up the other way in
other words you make a probability a
half that they're all lined up in one
way probability a half that they're all
lined up in the other way and sure
enough there will be a Sol solution
which will correspond to no
magnetization but that's a highly
unstable situation any small
stray very very tiny magnetic field
pointing either up or down will tend to
flip the magnets to the preferred in the
preferred direction and you will either
get this or this depending on which way
the um well two possibilities you'll
either get this or this depending on the
direction of that extremely weak
magnetic field now I have not included
that very weak magnetic field in the
calculation uh we could but that's just
a nuisance we simply know that if we
have a lot lot of spins and they all
want to line up and they're reinforcing
each other binding each other to be in
the same
direction uh that at low temperatures
they will tend to line up and either
they will line up positively or
negatively s will either be positive or
negative depending on nothing more than
the value of let's say an
infinitesimally small background
field which uh is of such insignificance
that we don't even need to worry about
it in the Dynamics of the
magnet there's a critical point the
critical
point the critical temperature is the
temperature or the beta over here which
makes the blue curve have the same slope
as the Black curve in other words it's
the first point it's a point at
which you're just on the cusp of having
spontaneous magnetization I didn't draw
that well over here I meant it to be
tangent to the uh to the black curve so
as I vary
beta I eventually hit a point where the
blue curve is tangent to the black curve
there's only one solution at that point
the magnetization is zero but then when
I just go Epsilon past that just a tiny
bit past that then the magnetization the
spontaneous magnetization happens and
that point is the critical point all
right it's the critical point and it's
the point where tanch has unit
slope so what does that mean what's the
slope of this tanch here at the origin
it's the derivative of tan with respect
to s so what's the derivative of tan
with respect to
S at the
origin I think it's just uh
twice twice beta
D so when twice beta D is that right I
mean if we differentiate tant can
anybody do
that all right let's do it let's do it
just to convince ourselves that I'm
right what is tan tan is cinch over Kash
right cinch over Kos so
cinch uh let's write just CCH X over Kos
X we differentiate first with respect to
X and then we'll differentiate x with
respect to the argument of the tangent
right just usual rule for calculating
derivatives the derivative of cinch is
Kash right so let's do uh what's the
usual rule denominator times the
derivative of the
numerator derivative of this with
respect to
X is equal to the denominator k
x uh times the derivative of the
numerator derivative of the numerator is
also c x c^ 2
x minus the numerator time the
derivative of the
denominator so I think that should be
minus sin 2
X plus or minus
we'll see in a
minute let's
see we have numerator sorry we have
denominator time the derivative of
numerator minus numerator time the
derivative of the denominator so it
looks to me like K squ minus sin squ
derivative of K is equal to cinch and
derivative of cinch is equal to Kos
as numerator is
one the numerator is one at xal
0 the numerator is one oh cos squ yeah
cos squ - x^ squ is 1 and this is just
equal to 1
over C of
x^2 okay so
um and that at x equals 0 right at this
point over here at xal 0 that's
one k of 0 is one so this is all equal
to the number one that's the derivative
of the T with respect to the argument
here but then we have to differentiate
differentiate the argument with respect
to S and that will give us a 2 Beta D so
that's where the 2 Beta D comes from the
derivative of this with respect to S at
the origin is 2 Beta D and when that
becomes equal to one
in other words when the derivative of
this curve just matches just kisses the
uh
the uh the 45 degree line here that's
the critical point or that determines
the critical temperature and so the
critical temperature let's see did I
miss a j out of
this wasn't there a a parameter J that
uh yeah yeah
ASAT yeah it's there there's a j there a
j
J all right so this is one over
temperature
here and if I shift it to the other side
of the equation it just gives me the
critical temperature the critical
temperature at which the
uh T critical is twice D * J notice
among other things that the critical
temperature gets higher with increasing
dimensionality why is that well low
temperature you're in the magnetized
phase the question is how long or how
high can you heat it before the
temperature thermal fluctuations disrupt
the magnetized phase and the answer is
the more neighbors that you have the
higher the temperature you can get to
before you'll escape from their um for
them from their tendance to hold you in
place so that's why the critical
temperature increases with d you get to
higher temperatures before the
magnetization disappears in higher D
it's proportional to J J was just the
strength of a coupling between
neighboring spins the stronger the
coupling between neighboring spins also
increases the temperature and the two
the two came from
someplace all right so now if
we if we
go back I know I explained this but
let's uh let's do it
again if we go back to the phase diagram
let's go back to the phase
diagram and the phase diagram is a
diagram which on the horizontal axis is
just the
temperature and the vertical axis is the
external magnetic field which may be up
or down it plays the role in uh in the
magnet
of the chemical potential in the fluid
all right so let's put vertically here
H and if H is less than
zero in other words the magnetic field
is pointing down it will bias all of the
spins down and throughout this
entire quadrant here the average spin
will be down that's for sure but if you
approach this line where H is equal to
zero it may or may not be that when you
just get to that line the
magnetization is still there or it may
be absent okay if it's there that means
there's a jump discontinuity because
certainly if you approach from the other
side you'll
find that the magnetization is positive
on this side negative on this side and
if there's anything left of it right at
the edge of this line here it will have
to jump and that's a first order phase
it's called A first order phase
transition it is the sort of thing that
happens as
you
increase the
density of a
gas the chemical potential can be used
to increase the density of the gas you
increase the density of the gas at fixed
temperature and eventually you'll go
from gas to liquid all right that's when
does that happen well it happens when
the molecules get good and close
together so that they're almost buting
up against each other not quite if
they're buting up against each other too
much of course what'll happen is it'll
freeze into a a crystal
lattice but somewhere in between
freezing and a crystal lattice and high
temperature boiling water uh uh
somewhere in between you'll have a jump
in density okay or a jump in the
magnetization if you go to too high a
temperature this is T critical as we've
seen if you go to too high a temperature
then the spontaneous magnetization
disappears over here and so the phase
diagram contains spontaneous
magnetization over
here and it disappears over
here as I said you can go I'm sure I did
say this but I need to remind myself as
well as
you I can go
from let's call it the downward
magnetized phase over here which is also
the gas phase let's call it the gas
or magnetization
negative over here
liquid magnetization greater than zero
you can go across this boundary in which
case you see a sudden jump there's no
doubt in that case that uh that you've
made a uh uh a jump in the uh in the
density or you can go around
here and pass from gas to liquid without
a
discontinuity so if you go around the
critical temperature of water around in
this way you uh increasing the density
you can avoid void the sudden
jump yeah uh in the case let's say
you're going from the bottom to the top
through the critical uh uh to the left
uh the the lower Arrow does that imply
that you're changing the magnetic field
at one one point no no no no no all over
all over all over okay right right what
we're doing is we're changing the
chemical potential changing the chemical
potential is a trick for changing the
density
right that's all it is it's a trick for
changing the density if you like you can
simply think of yourself as squeezing
the water keeping the temperature
fixed we don't even really have to keep
the temperature fixed in fact here I
didn't keep the temperature fixed it
wandered from here to here but if we
wanted to have a precise version of it
we might cross at a fixed temperature so
in that case you would be increasing the
pressure at the same time increasing the
density but keeping the temp what did I
say uh increase the pressure increase
the density but keep the system in
thermal equilibrium with its uh with its
environment so that the temperature
stays the same at some point the system
will jump from uh from gas to
uh uh from Vapor
to to liquid right so that's the basic
physics of the very simplest kind of
phase transition
so what do you see if you go around the
outside I can understand that if you can
press if you go around the outside to
the right you go around this way yeah if
you go the other way you see it go from
gas to liquid that makes sense but on
the top it's liquid and the bottom it's
gas so what do you see if you go around
you just see you just see gas
continuously change into liquid the
density increases at no point do you see
a sharp discontinuity between liquid and
gas the lesson is there is no sharp
discontinuity it there is no infinitely
sharp way to say this is a gas and this
is a
liquid you can go continuously from one
to the other without an Abrupt change
now this is not true for going to a
solid
something uh the solid liquid phase
transition has a different character um
what happens when you go from liquid to
ice let's say what happens when you go
from liquid to ice
you know both both the
uh you get a fog basically as you around
yeah you get a you get a kind of fog
with with a fog which gets denser and
denser and denser and then just becomes
uh
basically so so are you saying that if
both in liquid and solid stay like 5%
liquid 95% solid I mean liquid and gas
there would be no way to go from the
liquid and gas
continuously there's always an abrupt uh
an Abrupt uh change from from sorry from
from solid to liquid right right I I
meant gas to liquid so so when you go
around you basically got like a fog of
5% liquid yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah right
right right there's yeah there's little
droplets in it uh yeah you start down
here and it's mostly gas but there are
little droplets little droplets are part
of the gaseous phase having little
droplets if you look at it through a
microscope you'll find little droplets
in it okay but the little droplets come
and go what happens to them they form
and they evaporate they form and they
evaporate they form and they evaporate
likewise up
here sort of symmetrically the liquid
will sometimes have form little bubbles
of gas there'll be little bubbles of gas
but the little bubbles of gas will also
uh they won't evaporate but the liquid
will squeeze them out liquid will
squeeze them out and the little bubbles
of gas that accidentally form get
squeezed out and so there is a kind of
symmetry between these on one side you
have gas with little droplets of liquid
on the other side you have liquid with
little bubbles of gas but as you said as
you move around
here uh the little droplets of liquid
begin to become more
prominent they grow they they're are
more numerous and maybe bigger and a
little and the gaseous phase sort of
smoothly goes over to the liquid phase
but right along here right along here
you have sort of both liquid and gas at
the same time you have little lumps of
liquid little lumps of gas uh and so
forth just in the same way that if you
looked at the magnitude the magnet
through a microscope you would discover
islands of down Spin and islands of up
spin equally numerous uh uh along here
down here you would find more islands of
down spin up here you would form more
islands of up spin right on here you
would find an equal population and you
would go smoothly from one to the other
quite different what happens when you go
across here when you go across here
you'll see mostly gas or mostly down
spins until you get right to here and
then you jump to mostly uh mostly
upstairs in the case of the magnet the
the Y AIS is the magnetic field the
external magnetic field right and in the
case of the liquid and gas what is the Y
AIS the y- axis is the chemical
potential remember what the chemical
potential is is it's just a
device for increasing the
density it's a device for increasing the
density the bigger or smaller uh you
make the uh depends on your definition
but pushing the chemical potential one
way or the other tends to make it more
or less dense incre remember what the do
you remember what the chemical potential
was it was a you don't remember I don't
think you covered in this this
class oh I didn't uh explain what the
chemical potential is oh okay why don't
I do that right now okay good uh my
apologies Let's uh let's talk about
chemical
potential all right chemical potential
is
a
tool
for
problems let me erase the
Blackboard all right let's imagine we go
back to the very beginning where we have
a bunch of identical
boxes and remember what the game was we
allowed energy to be interchanged
between the Boxes by a weak interaction
which allow the boxes to uh to exchange
energy between them and then what we
calculated was the probability
distribution for a given
box uh given a total amount of energy in
the situation in equilibrium where they
come to equilibrium and when energy is
uh going back and forth at equal rates
so it's at
equilibrium then uh then there's some
total energy and given the total energy
we can calculate the probability
distribution
for a given box to have a uh uh now when
we did that we introduced we introduced
the temperature or the inverse
temperature as a lrange
multiplier we said we want to maximize
the entropy subject to a constraint and
this what was the constraint the
constraint was that the total amount of
energy was fixed so he said let's
maximize entropy given that uh that E1
plus E2 plus E3 blah blah blah blah blah
no that's not right that's not what I
want to
write I want to
write that the number of
boxes with energy E1 plus the number of
boxes with energy E2 and so
forth all add up to the total energy of
the
system e total
the number of boxes with energy E1 the
total energy that they have is n * E1 so
let's call that N1 N2 and so forth I'm
just just go back to your early notes I
just want to remind you and how did we
implement this constraint this was a
constraint we had a we had a problem of
minimizing or maximizing something we
wanted to maximize the
entropy I'm not going to go through it
we wanted to maximize the entropy given
that the total energy is
fixed the way to do that was to
introduce a lrange multiplier we
introduced the lrange multiplier I can't
remember now if it had a plus sign or a
minus sign but we call that lrange
multiplier
beta and that beta multiplied sum n subi
e
subi or well that's good enough that's
that's what we did we went through this
we maximized the
entropy and what do we find we found
that the probability distribution the
probability distribution for a given box
was e to the minus beta time the
energy and if we want to normalize it we
had to put one over the partition
function there now that's just back to
First back to first uh lecture or second
lecture or whatever it was now supposing
that it is also possible not just for
energy to be exchanged between these
boxes but particles to be
exchanged uh helium atoms if this was
helium for example or whatever it
happens to be or water molecules if it's
water in other words there's little thin
pipes
here little thin pipes and those little
thin pipes allow water or fluid to be
exchanged back and forth then we will
not know with um absolute certainty what
the number of particles in each box was
remember that we've assumed previously
that each box had a given number of
particles but now we don't know what the
number of particles is in the Box it
also has a probability
distribution it also has a probability
distribution but here now is what we
will have to do we will have to add two
lrange multipliers we have
to the the one lrange multiplier is for
the total energy and so that's summation
of N Sub i e sub
I incidentally the N Sub I if you
remember were proportional to the
probability what was I in this formula
anybody
remember which box no not which box not
which
box okay let me I'll remind you because
you probably have forgotten by now so
have I okay what n subi and ESI were
each box can be in any one of a whole
bunch of States here are all the states
energy here's the first state the second
state the third state the fourth state
and so forth the states are labeled by
I insabi is the number of
boxes that occupy the I state are the
number of boxes in which you will find
the system and the I
State n subi times the energy at the I
state if I sum it over all
I that gives me the total
energy it's the number of boxes in the
first state times the energy of the
first state plus the number of boxes in
the second state times the energy of the
second state and so forth and so on this
has to equal total energy
right that's first thing now do you
remember if there were inboxes here do
you remember the formula that N Sub I
over total n is equal to the probability
of the I
state in other words the probability
that any given box is in the I state is
just proportional to the
fraction of total number of boxes that
are occupying the I State and we call
that the
probability so we could divide this
formula I'll just go through it with you
again we could divide this formula by
n e total ided by n what's E total
divided by
n it's the average energy in any given
box so we'll just call this e the
average energy in a particular box and
this becomes summation over i p of I EI
I equals
the
energy this was a constraint this was a
constraint and what we want to do is to
maximize the
entropy maximize the entropy remember
what s is what's
s minus summation of i p of I log P of I
that was the entropy and we want to
maximize it subject to a constraint and
the way you do that is to introduce a
lrange multiplier beta if we get this
over here introduce a lrange multiplier
beta and then maximize this expression
with respect to Pi the pis are the
variables we're trying to find out what
the probability of the I state is we
want to maximize the entropy
subject to the constraint of a given
energy and if you remember we went
through it it gave us that
Pi is equal to
what e to minus beta e sub
I divided by z z is just there to make
the total probability add up to
one right that's the probability of
being in the I State now now we've done
something new we've allowed particles to
jump back and forth
for we've allowed particles to jump back
and
forth but the total number of particles
is not allowed to change the total
number of particles we'll assume is
conserved total number of helium atoms
or water molecules or whatever it is is
conserved and so we can write another
constraint the other constraint is that
uh the
um
that the
number of particles in the first box
let's let's see um the number of
particles in the first
box in one plus the number of particles
in the second box plus the number of
particles in the third box and so forth
not plus all have to add up to the total
number of
particles N1 N2 and N3 and so forth they
can change but the total number of
particles has to remain constant yeah
I just want when you did this the first
time you had two constraints yes yes yes
there was a yeah that was that wasn't
the number of particles it was the
number of boxes right yeah you're right
there was there actually were two
constraints that the total number of
boxes added up to n but uh that's right
all right I had hoped to uh to get
around that it's there all right so
there's another lrange multiplier that
has to be added and that lrange
multiplier instead of
multiplying the
energy multiplies the number of
particles in each box I'll tell you what
the net result is the net result is we
can now think of the
probability as a joint probability that
the system is in the I State and it has
n
particles it's not just a question now
of which Quantum State the system is but
also how many particles it has in
it so there's a probability which is a
function of the number of particles in
the box and also which of the many
Quantum States the box is in for that
many particles and the answer that you
get by the same exact analysis is
another term up in here which is
minus
beta
mu times the number of particles in the
Box this beta time mu is a somewhat
artificial
decomposition you could have just called
beta and mu the original lrange
multiplier it's beta time mu which is
the lrange multiplier it's just a
historical
definition that uh that this wasn't
called a single thing beta time mu but
uh that's the way it is that's the way
it is is all
right what does beta what does Mew do
for you what does tuning Mew do for you
well first of all muw is very much like
a temperature or beta time
mu uh this combination here is like a
temperature but what does temperature do
for you forget this what does
temperature what does changing
temperature
do it allows you to tune the
energy right by changing the temperature
if you know you had a given amount of
energy the way you would deal with this
is you would change beta until the
average energy is equal to the average
energy that you think is in the box so
beta is the tuning device the
temperature is the tuning device the
knob that you change to change the
energy in the
Box mu is the knob that you change to
change the number of particles in the
box
right mu is the knob that you change if
you want to change the number of
particles in the box and why is that
well you can see if the
probability let's forget this ter Factor
over here if the probability goes as e
to the minus beta mu * n then the
average number of particles in the box
is going to be controlled by this mu
here let's see the smaller mu is the
more particles will be in the box or
whatever it is so chemical potential is
just a device
for tuning the number of particles in a
box in a situation where the number of
particles in the Box can fluctuate or
change in one way or
another all right I I didn't want to
spend a lot of time on that but let's
come back to here
now how do you change
mathematically in terms of the
statistical mechanical partition
function in terms of the statistical
mechanical partition function how do you
change oh incidentally the partition
function Z let's let's think about the
partition function
Z the partition function Z
satisfies Z is equal to the
sum over all of the states of the system
and the number of particles in the box
number of particles in the box and the
various states that the particles can be
in of e to the minus beta e
subi minus beta mu times the number of
particles in the Box
that's just to make sure that the total
probability adds up to one so that's Z
and notice it has a new thing in it it
has a thing which allows you to control
the number of particles called a
chemical is the capital N in that
formula is supposed to be N Sub I no
it's so no it's the number of particles
in all the Box the average number of
particles in in all the boxes that's
right the average number of particles in
all the boxes all right so this is a
device and how do you choose mu you
choose mu by calculating the average
number of particles from this
probability distribution and then set it
equal to what you think the average
number of particles is whatever it
happens to be by changing by changing mu
yeah is the possible number of particles
in the Box because n can be anywhere in
this formula it's the it's the possible
number of particles in the Box anything
from zero to that's right and you sum
and you sum over it but you can also use
this now to calculate the average number
of particles how would you calculate the
average number you take the probability
distribution multiply it by in and sum
so you also have a formula for the
average number of particles in the
box right so if you know there are alog
together in total particles Al together
divided up among all the boxes then you
think you know what how many how many
particles should be in each box you
simply tune mu until you get that many
particles yeah but obviously tuning the
number of particles in a given box of a
given size is the same as changing the
density you can uh you can think about
how to do that you just divide by the
volume and so the chemical potential is
a trick in the partition function for
changing the density of the gas
poal what is that mu is the chemical mu
is the chemical potential and I have a
strong feeling that my definition of mu
differs from everybody else's on Earth
by a sign I discovered that sign the
other day i' been going out through my
entire life with a chemical potential
having the sign that I've given it here
I'm not going to try to correct it now
whatever it is it is the thing which
allows you to vary the uh uh the
density now what is the density in this
lattice fluid the density in the lattice
fluid is roughly speaking the number of
UPS spins divided by the volume capital
N becomes the number of up spins here A
Down spin is empty an upspin represents
a
molecule so capital N is just the number
of UPS spins how do you change the
number of UPS spins how do you tune the
system from essentially no UPS spins and
bias it towards lots of UPS spins you
change
H when H is down it pushes all the spins
down no matter what the temperature is
if H is down it will bias the system
toward few ups spins and if you want to
change the density of up spins what you
do is move along this H axis so a the H
axis is closely connected it's
essentially the same as the chemical
potential and it's the thing that you
tune to change the density of the uh of
the gas the then density of the fluid
yeah quick question uh terminology is
the one look range multiplier beta and
the other range multiplier is beta mu
well yeah it's a historical fact we
could have just called it
Lambda okay so it's it's different than
beta it's different than beta and um
historically Lambda was set equal to
Beta time mu a little confusing there
yeah I know right uh we could have just
called it
Lambda but that wouldn't be that would
be ahistorical and it would be different
than the standard terminology so the
standard terminology is to replace
Lambda by Beta beta mu but think of beta
mu is itself a quantity incidentally you
calculate the average number of
particles by differen iting the
logarithm of the partition function with
respect to Mu differentiating with
respect to Mu well differentiating with
respect to Beta mu brings down an
n and allows you to calculate the
average number of particles so you
calculate the derivative of the
logarithm of the partition function with
respect to Beta mu and that gives you
the uh uh the mean number of particles
which is very similar to how we
calculated the mean energy differentiate
the log of the partition function with
respect to the beta similar idea okay uh
that's that is the basic setup for now
how do an experimentalist measure the
chemical potential I know how they do
temperature but how do you I'm not sure
you do measure the chemical potential
yeah
um how do you measure the chemical
potential I would I would say you
measure the density more likely than the
chemical potential
um I don't know I never think about
measur measuring the chemical potential
I think of it as a tunable parameter
that changes the density and the density
is the thing that you
uh the work function yeah it is the
amount of energy that it takes to remove
a system from the box yeah it is related
to the work function
so yeah how much energy it takes to
remove a particle from from a box
yeah it's true okay
so uh good but now I want to talk about
something very exotic extremely
interesting and took many years to
really get
right it has had an enormous influence
on statistical mechanics and Quantum
field Theory I can I doubt that uh
that's obvious to anybody in the room
what all of this has to do with Quantum
field Theory but let's uh let's not
worry about that it has to do with the
behavior of the system as you approach
the critical point let's say moving
along H equals z we don't even need H
equal we don't even need H for this here
we just move along from the high
temperature side getting closer and
closer to the critical point what is it
that happens at the critical point and
something very interesting happens at
the critical point uh the first the
first idea that you need in order to
understand the critical point is the
idea of a correlation length
we talked I think we talked did we talk
at all about the correlation
function no we didn't so I'll tell you
what the correlation function is when we
don't need to talk about how you
calculate it it's an average it's an
average of the
product of spins at two different points
let's say Sigma of a and sigma of B it's
the average value of the product of
Sigma a and sigma B
it measures the degree of correlation
between the spin at Point a and a spin
at point B because these could be two
points on the
latice they could be near each other
they could be far from each other what
happens if a is equal to B
incidentally Sigma squ is just equal to
one so the correlation function at the
origin let's call
it in other words when A and B are the
same point that's always equal to one
but now let's uh separate the points
okay all right so how do I calculate the
correlation function at these two
different points and let's imagine let's
go to extremely high temperatures let's
start at the high temperature end of
things all right not at the magnetized
phase but at the high temperature end
infinite temperature enormously high
temperature and what happens at very
high temperature they're jiggling around
like mad and the temperature is so high
that the bonds are not very potent at
holding the spins aligned with each
other so let's talk about the
correlation or the average of the
product of two spins neighboring to each
other at very very high temperature what
would you expect that it would be zero
zero because even if you freeze you can
think of it this way you can think of
calculating it by freezing this spin up
and then calculating in the presence of
the spin up calculating the average of
this
Spin and then that's the way you can
think about it it really represents the
probability that if this spin is up then
this spin is also up or also down some
average uh given that this one is up
what's the probability that this one is
up or down and that represents that's
the correlation function or or better
yet given that this one up is up what's
the average of this one all right so
what would you expect again at very high
temperatures just zero because they're
fluctuating completely independently
because the temperature is so high that
the bond joining these is
ineffective what happens as you start to
lower the
temperature as you start to lower the
temperature if this spin is up it will
bias this spin to also be up because the
energy will be lowered if they're
parallel if the spin is down it will
will also bias it so what starts to
happen is that Sigma time Sigma starts
to not be zero
anymore and in fact is usually positive
it's positive because if this spin is up
this one is more likely to be up so
Sigma time Sigma is positive if this
spin is down then this one is also more
likely to be down and so again Sigma *
Sigma is positive and so this
correlation
function between neighboring
points at moderately high temperatures
will stop being zero and be small but
non zero what
about the correlation function between
second nearest neighbors square square
than the one it'll be more or less
that's right it'll be more or less the
square of the correlation between first
nearest neighbors that's right that in
fact is about what it is okay what about
you go way way down the line
here and there's nothing special about
moving along the horizontal axis here we
can move vertical axis or we can move at
a 45 degree but what would you expect as
you move way down
here again you'll expect each time you
move you'll lose some
correlation and in fact you lose the
same fraction of correlation roughly
speaking and that means that this is
going to be exponential in the distance
between these points if each time you
lost let's say half the correlation if
the correlation between nearest
neighbors was a half and second nearest
neighbors was a quarter third nearest
neighbors was an eighth and so forth you
might expect that this would behave like
e to the
minus some parameter
M times the distance between them let's
call a distance between them D distance
means number of lattice sites between
them so when you're very very far
away very far away the correlation is
extremely weak exponentially weak when
you're close by the correlation function
is stronger the correlation is stronger
this m depends on the
temperature at very very high
temperatures the correlation Falls very
rapidly to zero let's imagine plotting
it at different
temperatures correlation function is
always one at D equals 0 so this is D at
extremely high temperatures the
correlation function just drops like a
bomb down to
zero and so by the time you get over to
the first lattice point it's it's
negligible small at at very high
temperatures and then it just stays
small gets even smaller smaller smaller
exponentially
what happens as you lower the
temperature as you lower the
temperature the correlation function
continues to drop as an
exponential but the rate in here at
which it falls becomes more and more
gradual as the temperature gets lower
the rate at which it the Falls becomes
more gradual and that means that m is a
function of
temperature m is a function of
temperature and what does it represent
it represents the distance that you have
to go out in order that the correlation
has dropped by a factor of
e right um how far do you have to go out
in order that the correlation function
is dropped by a factor of e that's what
m
represents it's also called the inverse
correlation length
the inverse correlation length the
correlation length is is the width of
this curve here the correlation length
is very very
small and M is very
large as you lower the temperature the
correlation length gets longer and
longer and the inverse correlation
function gets smaller and
smaller okay when m is very small all
this function very gradually goes to
zero okay so m is a function of T it
represents the inverse of the
correlation length correlation length
being the distance out to which you have
to go uh in order that the that you've
lost a factor of e in the
correlation and those are a set of
definitions but they're clearly a useful
def set of definitions and what the
correlation length tells you is it just
tells you exactly what it's says uh how
long how how far out on the
lattice will you feel the effect of
nailing one particular spin in place
supposing you nailed one particular spin
in place a given either up or down how
far away is it felt that's called a
correlation length and it's inverse to
this m of T So M of decreases obviously
decreases with
temperature correlation length increases
mft decreases okay yeah in all these
cases you're assuming there's nothing
between the two test points right yeah
am so you're making an assumption about
the density in there
implicitly that you're making an
assumption that it's it's not so dense
that you're squeezing uh dense in the
sense of uh particles on every latus
Point mhm so again dense in the sense of
particles on every lattice point oh
there could be there could be a particle
on every lattice point then uh then a
correlation could be so it's just a
superposition it's just a superposition
of all the effects then yeah but at very
high temperatures it uh with no chemical
potential you will not find that there's
a particle on every Point you'll find
it's about half
filled half
filled uh at at high temp temperatures
half filled half empty this doesn't that
depend on how finely you draw the
lce how finally you draw the lattice
no no we just we um
no I nothing depends on how I draw the
lattice drawing the lattice is just
uh I can draw it on a piece of paper I
can draw it on the Blackboard I can uh
draw it on the ceiling same
system the spin could be up or down so
at each at each point the lce the spin
could be up or down so half of them are
up and half right half of them are up
and half of them are down at high
temperatures typically yeah okay good uh
but the interesting thing is this
correlation length gets longer and
longer okay now imagine you now pass
below the critical point what happens to
the correlation function below the
critical
point let's think about that take Sigma
of a * Sigma of B
below the critical point and below the
critical point here we are below the
critical point we could be here or we
could be
here below the critical point the bias
of just one spin being up com is enough
to bias remember what happens at the
below the critical point is this sort of
instability that the tiniest little
perturbation which biases it one way or
the other will lock all the spins not
all the spins exactly into the same
direction but will bias all the spins so
that the average
magnetization uh is in one of the two
directions so supposing we freeze Sigma
a to be up and now we look at Sigma B
well the sample has been biased by Sigma
a and we're in the magnetized phase
we're below the critical temperature
and so what's going to happen is Sigma B
will on the average be in the same
direction as Sigma a but right out to
Infinity right out to Infinity one in
this magnetized phase here one spin
pointing up is enough to tell all the
others that on the average they will
point up that's what happens uh in uh to
this down below the critical temperature
so what we can say then is that Sigma a
sigma B will go to some constant some
positive
number positive number I don't know what
to call it let's just call it a
number
constant As you move further and further
away Sigma a sigma B will go to some
constant that constant will also depend
on the
temperature if you're at very low
temperatures
the spins will tend to align each other
rather rigidly if you're at zero
temperature the only two possibilities
are all spins up and all spins down what
happens to this at zero
temperature it's one if Sigma a is up
then Sigma B is up if Sigma a is down
then Sigma B is down so at zero
temperature let's uh let's approach now
I'm going to use red to approach from
the low temperature side this is what
happened from the high temperature side
and this always goes to zero as long as
the temperature was high enough but
now here's temperature zero what happens
at a little bit higher temperature
you're still in the magnetized phase and
you still go to a constant out here but
a little bit less constant things are
not rigidly held in place as
well eventually you come down to the
critical temperature
and as you get to the critical
temperature that's the temperature which
divides these two
behaviors what's the behavior here
exponentially decreasing
correlation what's the behavior here the
correlation function doesn't decrease
what divides them what divides them is
the critical behavior let's see I have a
trouble drawing it the critical
Behavior which is neither constant
at Infinity nor is it exponentially
falling every one of these
eventually
Falls exponentially every one of them
Falls exponentially what about this
critical one here what's in between
being constant and falling
exponentially well there's a lot of
things but uh H hyperbolic hyperbolic
means
what 1/x well how about just one/ X to a
power one/ d one/ d to a
power H Infinity Zer an Infinity is zero
yeah this this could this Falls and
falls and falls and Falls but it never
Falls as fast as an
exponential and it it fails to have a
finite limit at the end right so what is
known uh this requires a proof and it
requires some uh some work but what's
known is right at the critical point
right at that critical point this just
just falls off as a power law This falls
off gradually as a power law not as an
exponential that's the characteristic
critical behavior that the correlations
are long range sort of one over R to a
power for the two-dimensional icing
model it's one over one over distance to
the to the 1/8 so it gradually falls off
the number is not terribly
important okay so that that's one of the
things that happens at their critical
point now as you approach the critical
point imagine that you looked
microscopically at uh the
magnet the correlation length here the
fact that it has some size what it's
really telling you is that the magnet is
filled up
with Blobs of
spins bubbles of spins more or less
pointing in the same direction
there are Blobs of spins up there are
blobs down but they're not exactly all
up they're somewhat biased toward up
they're somewhat biased toward down over
here somewhat biased toward it up down a
kind of
Patchwork where the patches tend to be
about as big as the correlation length
if you take two points beyond the
correlation
length out way past the correlation
length there isn't much correlation
between them something over here is as
likely to be up or down if this is up
but if your two points are within one of
these
blobs then most likely they're pointing
the same direction all right so it's
this blob it's this formation of these
bubbles or Blobs of uh of
material could be L it's really what is
it it's liquid gas uh in the case of the
fluid or up spins and down spins in the
case of the
magnet uh these structures more or less
follow in size the correlation length so
this m of T is basically just the
inverse of the size of the blobs that
you would see if you looked carefully
size one yeah size 1 / M
right and as you get closer and closer
to the critical point
what happens to m is it goes to
zero M goes to zero it's no longer a
exponential but gives way to a power
law uh and that corresponds to m going
to zero all right or the correlation
length blowing up the correlation length
gets bigger and bigger bigger and bigger
blobs like this okay so that's one now
what happens
of course I should say
this that each one of these blobs is is
not a pure phase it is not pure all
spins up this one is not all spins down
this one just has a preference for UPS
this one has a mild preference for
Downs what happens as you get closer and
closer to the critical point two things
happen
first of all these blobs get bigger and
bigger but second of all they tend to
fade fade means they what's what's the
word when you put your your nice colored
shirt with lots of contrast through the
washing machine too many
times Well fade fade if you were to look
at this as you move closer and closer to
the critical point what you would see is
these blobs blowing up okay now you
could say all right let me just try to
restore some uh some just for
convenience let me squeeze the whole
thing down so that the blobs have the
same size I'll have to make the lattice
smaller right I'm just going to do that
I'm going to do it as I move closer and
closer to the critical point the blobs
indeed get bigger and bigger but just as
a matter of convenience so that I don't
have to draw the whole thing on a
Blackboard which is 20 mi long what I'll
do instead is rescale the whole diagram
so that the blobs remain the same
size the blobs remain the same size
moreover there are blobs within
blobs there are blobs within blobs
within blobs but the net
effect in the biggest blobs is to be on
the average upspin in the biggest Blobs
of the down spin type the net effect is
to be down spin so that's what the car
coration length is but what happens to
these blobs even if you plot them always
in such a way that their size looks the
same this is just an arbitrary rescaling
of the lattice just just so that we can
redraw it uh so that I don't have to run
out of the room to the next room out
there to get closer and closer to the
critical point instead we imagine in our
heads making the latus spacing much
smaller so that the blobs occupy more
and more lce spacing things okay but in
addition to the blobs getting bigger
they get fainter they get um what's the
right word bleached I think somebody
said
um faded faded like a putting your uh
your polka dot black and white shirt
through the dishwash not the dishwasher
the washing machine too many times I
don't uh and what will happen after a
while the contract
between the up blobs and the down blobs
will get weaker and weaker and weaker
that's what happens at the critical
point in fact at the critical point you
have Blobs of every size right at the
critical point when the biggest blobs
grow to Infinity there are still smaller
blobs the biggest blobs grow to Infinity
but are infinitely faded the next
biggest
blobs they're
still there they're still they're pretty
big they're not quite as faded smaller
blobs within
blobs not quite as faded as their
predecessors and smaller what happens at
the critical point is a kind of
self-similar fractal structure a
self-similar fractal structure that on
every scale if you look at it you see
the same
thing namely blobs within blobs than
blobs but as you look on smaller and
smaller scales the contrast the density
contrast gets stronger and
stronger if at the same
time that you rescale a lattice push the
temperature closer to the critical point
push the temperature closer to the
critical point rescale the
lattice okay and also rescale the
density the the contrast the contrast uh
you know you you have your television
and you turn down the contrast or turn
up the contrast as you look at smaller
and smaller
blobs if you turn down the contrast then
you literally see the same thing at
every
scale the only distinction between what
you see at one scale and another scale
is the intensity of the contrast between
the blobs if you allow for
that if you allow for the decrease or
the fading of the contrast
from as you re as you get closer and
closer to the critical point then what
you see is just a self-similar fractal
which looks the same on every
scale uh everybody know what I mean by
self-similar it it just means it looks
the same at every scale you could not
tell by looking at it through a
microscope unless your microscope of
course was strong enough to see the
actual lattice structure I'm assuming we
have a microscope which can't see the
actual lattice structure but it sees
blobs then you at the critical point at
the critical point you cannot tell or
close to the critical point you cannot
uh tell how big the well you can't tell
which blobs you're looking at they all
look the same except for the strength of
the density contrast the smaller they
are the uh the smaller they are the
stronger the density contrast in fact if
you get down to the lattice spacing
itself you will see up spins and down
spins up spins are absolutely black down
spins are absolutely white and so you'll
see uh spins next to each other slightly
biased maybe but with very strong uh
contrast on the other hand these very
big lumps here those very big lumps will
have
weak uh contrast in fact the fact that
the contrast gets more and more faded is
just the fact that this correlation
function gets smaller and smaller as the
distance between things gets
big as the distance between points gets
big right at the critical point there
are Blobs of every
size but if you take two points the
correlation will mainly be due to Blobs
of about the scale between the two
points
what is it that will that what is it
will that will lead to a correlation
between these two points the likelihood
that there's a blob about that
big the further apart you take them
you'll be sampling bigger and bigger
blobs but bigger and bigger blobs have
less contrast and that's why the
correlation function Falls and goes to
zero because for very very big blobs the
the contrast has faded you can actually
see this in simulations of magnetic
systems you look at the simulations and
you see you know patterns of blobs and
blobs and blobs inide blobs it's hard to
really see anything more or less you see
white noise or black noise or whatever
but if you look carefully you can see
some slightly overdense regions some
slightly underdense regions and then as
you tune the system toward the critical
point the overdense regions and the
underdense regions grow and you also see
that they have blobs inside them which
are even more overdense and blobs ins
side blobs inside blobs and so this
pattern of
self-similarity uh is the
first thing that happens at the critical
point something else happens at the
critical point if you look at these
blobs the theory of these blobs the
actual Crystal the actual lattice itself
was not very symmetric certainly did not
have circular
symmetry it has just Square symmetry
it's a square lattice for example and so
it's not isotropic it's by no means
isotropic and you would not expect the
properties of the uh of the
magnet to look isotropic you wouldn't
expect the correlation function to be
truly isotropic you would expect it to
be different along the axes than it is
along the 45 degree
angles but as you get closer and closer
to the critical point the system loses
memory of the basic underlying lattice
Theory and it just gets more and more
rotationally symmetric more and more
isotropic until right at the critical
point by looking at these big big blobs
you cannot tell which direction the
lattice is oriented so that's another
thing that happens a wash out of the
basic starting point if you like the
basic starting point being some specific
lat
uh with a given
orientation I'll give you another
example we might have made a more
complicated structure instead of the
magnet having only nearest neighbor
coupling we might have had a lattice
with nearest neighbor and second nearest
neighbor coupling
or neighboring
couplings this spin times this spin but
maybe also diagonal couplings
spins uh energy of the
spins depending on diagonal couplings
and maybe second nearest neighbor
couplings and so forth we might have
invented a more complicated
model Sigma time Sigma nearest neighbor
plus Sigma time Sigma time nck nearest
neighbor and so
forth uh let's suppose that all the
bonds favor parallel spins let's suppose
that it tends to favor parallel spins
then there are detailed differences
between a magnet with second nearest
neighbor couplings
and um first nearest neighbor couplings
are in detail different the details of
the thermodynamics are
different and in particular they're
quite different at high temperatures
where the correlation length is very
small
uh the uh in general the details of the
lattice and the details of the structure
will be remembered at the high
temperature
limit but as you lower the temperature
and these blobs get bigger and bigger
the system starts to forget what the
details were so the critical behavior of
the second nearest neighbor coupled
lattice is exactly the same as the
critical behavior of the first nearest
neighbor couple lattice the diagonal
bonds don't do very much they may shift
what they will do is they will shift the
critical temperature a little
bit the uh the effect of changing the
bonds and the nature of the microscopic
uh interaction between molecules it will
have the effect in general that it may
change the critical temperature a little
bit but whatever the critical
temperature is as you approach it
whatever it is you'll always see exact
exactly the same pattern of fractal self
similar type of
structure which will forget the details
of the lattice that's the nature of
critical
Behavior bubbles or blobs at every
length scale stronger ones at small
length scale more faded ones at large
length scale contrast going down and
down and down uh there's an interesting
experimental consequence of this has
anybody ever seen critical opalescence
critical opalescence is a wonderful
phenomenon if you take a liquid helium
is a good example but any transparent
liquid and you tune its temperature
toward the critical point you tune
temperature and density Move Along here
getting closer and closer to the
critical
point what happens is exactly this Blobs
of every length scale form of every
length scale and the effect is that it
scatters light light passing through it
will be scattered at every
wavelength every wavelength will be
scattered pretty much the same way as
every other
wavelength if you're away from the
critical point the largest blobs will
have some given size and wavelengths
longer than that will not be
scattered okay but as you tune toward
the critical wave critical point longer
and longer wavelengths will be scattered
and light passing through a material IAL
close to its critical point just uh it's
called critical opalescence you can
imagine what that means it means uh how
would you describe opalescence
um well it all colors all colors it gets
very milky you have a filter H you have
a filter you have a filter filter a
filter a filter well you have a filter
but the point is that it scatters light
uh it scatters light that uh as you if
you're close to the critical point but
not that close you'll scatter all
wavelengths down to um microwaves get
closer to the critical point and you'll
start scattering radio waves I'm I'm
being a little bit extreme but uh at
first you scatter Optical light then you
scatter Optical light and infrared then
you start scattering Optical light
infrared microwaves then you start
scattering in everything and the whole
thing just looks like a Milky um
opalescent material it loses its
transparency because it just scatters at
every
wavelength so that's called critical
opalescence and it's a real phenomenon I
wish I had I wish I could show it to you
here but I don't have any liquid helium
I think liquid helium is probably the
best this is this is approaching the
critical mass by cooling to
it by by cooling or by heating it
doesn't matter really but uh but uh I
think it's uh best to do it by
cooling yeah and normally it would be
done by Cooling you would start above
the critical temperature and slowly cool
down to the critical temperature and as
you cool down you'll discover the thing
becomes a better and better scatterer of
light uh for it doesn't really absorb
the light it just becomes um not opaque
there's another word uh what's in
between opaque and transparent
translucent translucent becomes
translucent but translucent at every uh
at every way would that be because of
the different refractive index between
the solid I mean the the liquid and the
refra IND scales yeah yeah yeah yeah
there's a difference between the index
of refraction and the liquid and the uh
and so it scatters the light uh yes and
at all scales there are structures there
at all scales that uh that scatter the
light right
exactly and uh in fact one word that's
used to describe this self-similarity is
It's called scale invariance scale
invariance means the phenomena of things
looking the same at every scale but but
as a rule you have to keep in mind that
uh that the contrasts tend to fade and
so you have to artificially jack up as
you look at the bigger and bigger things
you have to artificially renormalize is
the word
renormalize the density
contrast uh so as to keep it the same
then what you see at every length scale
is the
same um question about the fading um I'm
trying to understand it so if you have
100 molecules or whatever if like the
ratio is like 97 or spin up and three
spin down that's very contrasty if it's
8515 that's less more faded would
wouldn't that be just the entropy of it
is certainly connected to entropy but
the fact that this correlation function
Falls at large distances like a power
law tells you that uh the intensity of
the or the contrast within a blob of a
of a Big Blob is less than the uh the
intensity of
the contrast of a smaller blob so that's
that's exactly what this falling
correlation function tells
you so it's a pretty interesting
phenomenon and um more than interesting
it's sort of at the root of how Quantum
field Theory works but we haven't talked
about Quantum field
Theory uh uh and it is the ingredient in
many approximate schemes many
approximate schemes you take a system
which you expect at the end to be
isotropic and homogeneous you're really
talking about some isotropic homogeneous
uh thing a Quantum field Theory would be
a case in point where things are
rotationally symmetric translationally
symmetric and so forth and you want to
model it you want to model it as a
system on a lattice
why because it's convenient to to to
replace the continuous distribution of
field variables that fill Space by an
approximate uh version of the theory
where all the degrees of freedom live on
individual ltic sites right what's going
to happen well you're going to wind up
with a description where the lattice
Behavior will stick through and get in
your way the system will not look
translated invariant because the lattice
is not translationally invariant there
will be Corners to things because the
lattice has corners but how do you
restore in such a system the behavior
that you were looking for in the first
place which was this smooth
translationally invariant rotationally
invariant Behavior and the answer is you
tune yourself to a critical point
whatever the whatever the example is
whether it's statistical mechanics or
Quantum field Theory you tune the
parameters until until you get to a
point where the correlation length is
much much longer than the lattice
length and that that limit the artifacts
the lattice artifacts disappear so this
is a common tool in Quantum field
Theory
uh and in statistical mechanics and so
forth okay so let's see where are we uh
any questions yeah I got one is this
related to Super conductivity in any way
uh not particular
particularly
um not particularly this is called
incidentally the rescaling that I've
described here this rescaling and
constantly pushing the blobs back to the
same size that's called renormalization
group it's got to do with
renormalization in Quantum field Theory
does it have to do well uh yes and no
um in some systems there is a phase
transition in a super fluid or in a
superconductor which behaves exactly
this way yeah but it's but it's not
really um got much to do with the with
the phenomena of super conduct
superconductivity
itself yeah are there applications of
this to cosmology like the microid
background radiation yes yes my yes
there we are um the right that's a good
point um
the fluctuations that are seen in the
sky the microwave background is very
homogeneous of course extremely
homogeneous or isotropic across the sky
but if you look at the level of 10 to
the
minus5 you see over densities and under
densities and so
forth in other words you see blobs you
see a
blobbin and in fact you see the same
blobbin at every scale you see exact ly
the sort of self similar scale invariant
uh kind of behavior as at a critical
point now is it connected with critical
points yes it is but not in a completely
obvious way but it is it it it looks
very much what what is seen in the sky
when you look at the microwave
background and you see these uh maps of
the microwave background and so forth is
self-similar in the same way that the
critical point uh self-similar or scale
invariance scale invariant is a word
that's used so it's almost as though the
early Universe was generated from a
Monte Carlo simulation Monte Carlo just
means a statistical averaging of a uh of
a magnetic system but that's not the
real reason for it the real reason for
it is quite different we didn't uh we
didn't uh the organization in the sky
did not come from a second or to phase
transition
incidentally uh jumping across here
where you have a real jump the density
that's called a first order phase
transition the order of the
transition the lowest order transition
corresponds to the biggest most abrupt
jump so A first order phase transition
is one in which density or magnetic
field or whatever the appropriate
variable is the obvious variable makes a
discontinuous jump if you approach along
here along the temp temperature axis
with no bias you come right down to this
critical point over here and then if you
go a little bit further you'll see
spontaneous
magnetization here you don't see
anything
discontinuous right at this point over
here the magnetization is zero and as
you move in the magnetization the
magnitude of the magnetization
continuously increases so there's no
sudden jump in the magnetization here
it's just 0 0 000000 0 and then it
starts increasing from here but smoothly
that's called a second order phase
transition when the density or
magnetization uh is absolutely zero
until a critical point and then starts
to increase smoothly from
there uh something is discontinuous over
at this point over here if you
differentiate the magnetization enough
times you will find that there's some
singularity in it but it's a subtle it's
a more subtle effect second order phase
transitions are more subtle and third
order phase transitions are even more
subtle and almost never happen because
they're so
subtle okay
yeah I can't think of one off hand I
once new one I don't remember what it
was uh but they're they're rare and I
don't off off hand I cannot remember
what the what system had a third or
phase transition yeah uh the chemical
opalescence
phenomenon is that's what happen
critical opis critical
critical is that what's happening when a
lot of vapor condenses in the
clouds
well I don't think no
um no no uh it's
not um it sort of looks like it but it's
not the critical point anybody know what
the critical temperature of water is
also something like that I don't
remember exactly but it's you know way
way above oil it's about 300
36 360° something like see
306° right so this temperature here is
at
306° and some and some pressure some
pressure and some
temperature uh or some uh some density
in some temperature some density in some
temperature there's a critical point and
that critical point is the second order
phase transition and you know if you
want to see it you got to in water you
have to be up at 306 degrees on the
other hand in helium it happens at a
very low temperature much lower
temperature and so you can see uh liquid
helium boiling into helium vapor and if
you bring the helium to just the right
uh density and uh temperature you can
see the critical opalescence
okay uh when in the cosmology example if
you look at uh over time when um Dark
Energy thing took over from the um from
the matter not could that be considered
like a critical point as well no
transition no that uh no that's not a
critical point any kind of critical fact
in cosmology uh
the main analog of this kind of critical
behavior is What's called the scale
invariant fluctuation
Spectrum uh the spectrum of fluctuations
and perturbations over densities and
under densities that were there at
primordial times before galaxies formed
just uh the surface of last scattering
surface of last scattering if you look
out on the sky looks like this kind of
uh behavior and I mean quantitatively
quantitatively it looks scale
invariant now it's it's actually not
completely true because the system gets
processed a little bit I mean it's quite
obvious that gravity took over and
started manipulating the overdense and
the underdense
regions but if we could have seen what
that sky was like before gravity started
to work on these overdense and there the
real primordial fluctuation Spectrum it
would look very much like the uh the
critical point of this
magnet um on inflation I hear when you
go from the uh I guess the high the
vacuum the vacum on steroids the really
high one down to the regular one I've
heard that they had some original Pro
problem with the theory Alex reheating I
uh that's called reheating reheating
yeah why reheating and not just Heating
said and it didn't make any sense to me
then but they said it was originally
modeled as a first order phase
transition oh oh oh okay yeah uh right
we can talk about that next time a
little bit remind me um yes it was
originally modeled as a first order
phase transition that was a
disaster and I can tell you why we have
enough uh things I can tell you why but
I'm not going to tell you why now
uh I'm I'm fading my contrast is
diminishing
for more please visit us at stanford.edu